Guide to the William Harrison Hamman Papers, 1828-1966 MS 006
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William Harrison Hamman papers
1828-1966, bulk dates 1861-1889
1861-1889
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Hamman, William Harrison, 1830-1890
MS 006
6 Linear Feet 12 boxes plus oversize items
Correspondence, documents, Civil War materials, clippings, and other papers of Hamman including accounts of early Texas historical events and political opinions as well as his legal and business papers regarding oil land, gas, and minerals; together with papers of his wife, Ella Hamman; papers of John Hamman (1879-1966), founder of Hamman Exploration Col, later Hamman Oil and Refining Co., pioneer in the development of mineral resources in Texas, and lawyer specializing in land and corporation law; and papers of other family members. Includes material relating to Hamman's service with 4th Texas Infantry. Persons represented include Sam Houston and Robert E. Lee.
Biographical Note
William Harrison Hamman, soldier, farmer, lawyer, and entrepreneur, was born at Woodstock, VA on January 17, 1830, the son of George and Catherine Schmucker Hamman. His father, a carpenter, died when William was ten years old, and William worked various numerous jobs to help support his family. He attended the University of Virginia in 1850 and 1851, studying mathematics, German and chemistry. He was commissioned a second lieutenant in the Virginia militia on April 13, 1850, and promoted to captain on November 8, 1856. In January 1858 he moved to Owensville in Robertson County, TX, and on September 21 was licensed to practice law there.
Through the 1850s he had been an ardent Unionist and strongly opposed Virginia's secession. On December 15, 1860, he was a leader in Robertson County calling for the immediate secession of Texas. With the outbreak of the Civil War, Hamman enlisted on July 15, 1861, as a private in the "Robertson Five Shooters", which soon became Company C, Fourth Texas Infantry of the famed Hood's Texas Brigade. Hamman was first elected to corporal and then, on October 16, 1861, to regimental color sergeant. He was appointed acting regimental commissary sergeant in July 1862 and served as regimental commissary officer from August 6, 1862, until the Confederate government in August 1863 abolished the position. That month he applied for a mission to return to Texas, and was dispatched as a messenger to the Trans-Mississippi Department. He remained in Texas and was appointed on December 25, 1863, aide-de-camp to the commander of the First Brigade, Second Division, Texas State Troops. On March 12, 1864, he was promoted to captain of the Texas State Troops and appointed adjutant general of the Fifth Brigade District. He rose to the rank of brigadier general on December 26, 1864.
Although his means were reduced by the war, in 1866 Hamman became the first oil prospector in Texas; he drilled his first oil well at Saratoga in Hardin County. Ironically, he owned options and leases at the Sour Lake and Spindletop oilfields, but did not drill on them. In August 1870 Hamman helped to incorporate three business enterprises - the Calvert Bridge Company, to build a safe and substantial bridge over the Brazos River at Calvert; the Pacific and Great Eastern Railway Company of Texas, to build a rail link between the Red River and the Rio Grande; and the Texas Timber and Prairie Railroad Company, to build a railroad between Beaumont and Bremond. In May of that year he also helped charter the Calvert and Belton Railroad. In 1871 Hamman moved to Calvert when the Houston and Texas Central Railroad reached town. There he established a successful legal practice. On July 26, 1871, he married Ella Virginia Laudermilk. The couple had five children.
In 1878 Hamman, theretofore a Democrat, became interested in monetary reform and ran as the Greenback party's candidate for governor, finishing second; he ran again in 1880 and finished third. In 1889 he became interested in the development of the coal and iron deposits at New Birmingham in Rusk County and helped organize the Cherokee Coal and Iron Company. Hamman died at New Birmingham on July 14, 1890, and was buried in the Owensville Cemetery, Calvert, Texas.
Excerpted from The New Handbook of Texas, 1996
Scope and Contents
Consists of twelve boxes as well as some oversize material. A collection of documents, letters, Civil War materials, newspapers, and other miscellaneous material, connected with Brigadier General William Harrison Hamman (1830-1890), who lived in Texas during the Secession, Civil War, Reconstruction, and Bourbon period.
The collection includes contemporary accounts of early Texas historical events and political opinions, as well as Hamman's legal and business papers (regarding oil land, gas, and minerals, etc.). Also included are the papers of Mrs. Ella Hamman; John Hamman (1879-1966), founder of the Hamman Exploration Company, which later became Hamman Oil and Refining Company, and a pioneer in the development of mineral resources in Texas, as well as a lawyer specializing in land and corporation law; and other Hamman family members.
Materials in the collection are foldered in paper and some oversize material has been encapsulated.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. John Hamman, Jr., received in April, 1967.
Index Terms
Subjects
Petroleum industry and trade; Law and legislation; Natural gas; Mines and mineral resources; Law and legislation; Women -- Texas -- Biography; Women
Places
United States; Texas
Subjects (Persons)
Hamman, William Harrison, 1830-1890; Houston, Sam, 1793-1863; Hamman, John, 1879-1966; Hamman, Ella; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Hamman family
Subjects (Corporations)
Hamman Oil and Refining Co.; Hamman Exploration Co.; Confederate States of America. Army. Texas Infantry Regiment, 4th.
- Series I: W.H. Hamman - Personal papers, etc., 250127
  - Biographical sketch of General William H. Hamman, n.d.; 250146 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of W.H. Hamman, n.d.; 250145 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: entry into and diplomas from the University of Virginia, 1850-1851; 250144 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - W.H. Hamman and George C. Hamman, 1858-1860; 250143 (Box 1)
  - Personal ledgers, notes, account books, 1859-1875; 250142 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - W.H. Hamman and Ella V. Lawdermilk, 1867-June, 1871; 250141 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - W.H. Hamman and Ella Hamman, Dec. 1871-1887; 250140 (Box 1)
  - Certificates admitting practice in the federal courts and the state courts, 1872-1873; 250139 (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence - unidentified, 1872-1881; 250138 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - W.H. Hamman and George Hamman (son), including report cards and correspondence re: George's school, 1888-1890; 250137 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to, from, or re: Katie Hamman Stricker (particularly her education), 1889-1890; 250136 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, etc. from G.R. Hamman re: farm, 1889-1890; 250135 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, etc. from J.S. Hamman re: farm and crops, 1890-1895; 250134 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, etc. re: W.H. Hamman's death (includes letters of condolence and material re: Cooney trial), 1890; 250133 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: W.H. Hamman estate, 1890-1898; 250132 (Box 1)
  - Personal Library lists, n.d.; 250131 (Box 1)
  - Article re: school in Owensville where W.H. Hamman was a guest speaker, n.d.; 250130 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified poem, n.d.; 250129 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Schmuker graves, n.d.; 250128 (Box 1)
- Series II: W.H. Hamman - Civil War and Political material, 250078
  - Letter and discharge of Francis Holland, 1836; 250126 (Box 2)
  - Soldier's discharge, Nov. 22, 1839; 250125 (Box 2)
  - W.H. Hamman's commissions in the Virginia Militia, 1850-1857; 250124 (Box 2)
  - Speech given by W.H. Hamman in Woodstock, Virginia (July 4, 1857) with related correspondence, 250123 (Box 2)
  - R.R.B's Southern Platform, August 9, 1860; 250122 (Box 2)
  - Copy of Resolution by Legislature, Nov. 28, 1860; 250121 (Box 2)
  - Political letter from W.H. Hamman to Jacob H. Kibler, Dec. 10, 1860; 250120 (Box 2)
  - Broadside re. Secession Convention, ca. 1860; 250119 (Box 2)
  - Resolutions re. secession of Texas (Robertson County Meetings), ca. 1860-1861; 250118 (Box 2)
  - Poll Book of Voters in Owensville re. Presidential Electors, Delegates to Texas General Convention, and Referendum on Secession, 1860-1861; 250117 (Box 2)
  - Ordinance to Dissolve the Union, Feb. 1, 1861; 250116 (Box 2)
  - Letter to John Marshall reporting on speeches given by members of the Democratic Party., ca. 1861; 250115 (Box 2)
  - CSA records, 1861-1864; 250114 (Box 2)
  - W.H. Hamman's Commission in Confederate Army, Assistant Commissary, Fourth Texas Infantry, Nov. 4, 1862; 250113 (Box 2)
  - Confederate bond and money, 1862-1864; 250112 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence re. commissions in Confederate States Army (with photocopies), 1862-1865; 250111 (Box 2)
  - The Sentinel Daily, Richmond Va. (photocopy), August 19, 1863; 250110 (Box 2)
  - Papers re. commission and discharge of J.C.C. Brettell in Texas Calvary of CSA., 1863; 250109 (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of title page: Rifle and Infantry tactics, 1863; 250108 (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of title page: The Judge Advocate's Vade Mecum, 1863; 250107 (Box 2)
  - W.H. Hamman's commission to rank of Captain, 5th Brigade Texas (photocopy), August 4, 1864; 250106 (Box 2)
  - W.H. Hamman's commission to office of Brigadier General, 5th Brigade District, TST (photocopy), Dec. 28, 1864; 250105 (Box 2)
  - Broadside re. Civil War sentiment and troops, March 18, 1865; 250104 (Box 2)
  - Discharge of John C. Wilson from the United States Army, June 22, 1865; 250103 (Box 2)
  - Proclamation of Andrew J. Hamilton, Sept. 8, 1865; 250102 (Box 2)
  - Amnesty certificate of Thos. Aycock, Sept. 11, 1865; 250101 (Box 2)
  - Post Civil War letter from W.H. Hamman to Caroline (?) (photocopy), Nov. 18, 1865; 250100 (Box 2)
  - Speech of W.H. Hamman as candidate for Texas Senate, 1865; 250099 (Box 2)
  - W.H. Hamman's Voter Registration slips, 1871-1874; 250098 (Box 2)
  - Printed election circulars (most involving Robertson County Politics), 1872-1875; 250097 (Box 2)
  - Petition to State Senate and House of Representatives for citizens of Robertson County, 1875?; 250096 (Box 2)
  - Political Speeches and correspondence re. Greenback Party and campaign of 1880, 1876-1890; 250095 (Box 2)
  - Political Pamphlets - Union Greenback party, ca. 1879; 250094 (Box 2)
  - National Platform of the Greenback Labor Party, June 10, 1880; 250093 (Box 2)
  - Synopsis of political speech at Brenham, Oct. 16, 1880; 250092 (Box 2)
  - Letter from E.W. Morton re. formation of a new party, Dec. 12, 1882; 250091 (Box 2)
  - Letter of recommendation for L.B. Jones, and letter of support to Charles M. Anton, Feb. 18, 1889; 250090 (Box 2)
  - Declaration of Principles, 1890?; 250089 (Box 2)
  - Letter from E.L. Donahue urging attendance at convention, Feb. 3, 1890; 250088 (Box 2)
  - Notes on War, n.d.; 250087 (Box 2)
  - Certificate of membership in Hoods Texas Brigade (photocopy), n.d.; 250086 (Box 2)
  - Autographed photograph of Robert E. Lee; receipt signed by Robert E. Lee, n.d.; 250085 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous speeches given by W.H. Hamman, n.d.; 250084 (Box 2)
  - Letter to editor of newspaper re. Sam Houston, n.d.; 250083 (Box 2)
  - Post script Reply to Foster Brigance criticizing treatment of mail, n.d.; 250082 (Box 2)
  - James Madison's signature?, n.d.; 250081 (Box 2)
  - Programme of a course of lectures on temperance and reform, 250080 (Box 2)
  - Clippings from Civil War newspapers, n.d.; 250079 (Box 2)
- Series III: W. H. Hamman - Business and Legal papers (Boxes 3-10), 249927
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, correspondence, notes, etc., re. land, 1828-1893; 250077 (Box 3)
  - Land title and related correspondence - Antanacia de la Serda, ca. 1832; 250076 (Box 3)
  - Translation of title papers - Juan Jose Acosta, 1832; 250075 (Box 3)
  - Legal Papers and correspondence re. title to original land grant of Francisco Antonio Ruiz (with translation of title), 1833 - 1875; 250074 (Box 3)
  - Deeds, legal papers and correspondence re. Joseph Welch League, Robertson County, 1834 -1885; 250073 (Box 3)
  - Spanish title and related correspondence re. Head right of Creed T. Thompson, 1835 - 1894; 250072 (Box 3)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land - Joshua G. Smith, 1835 - 1905; 250071 (Box 3)
  - Translated title of land and related correspondence - Jose Antonio de Pena, 1836 - 1875; 250070 (Box 3)
  - Legal document grantin Chas. S. Walden agent of David A. Thompson, July 9, 1838; 250069 (Box 3)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land - John S. Gooch, 1838 - 1858; 250068 (Box 3)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. G.M.G. Grafton League in Robertson County, 1838 - 1875; 250067 (Box 4)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land - Francis Holland, Jr. and Tapley Holland, 1838 - 1884; 250066 (Box 4)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land - Joel Burt, 1838 - 1887; 250065 (Box 4)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. John Haynie league, 1844 - 1889; 250064 (Box 4)
  - Legal papers and correspondence of Brettell and Hamman Law firm (includes account book), 1849 - 1891; 250063 (Box 4)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land - Dawson, 1851 - 1886; 250062 (Box 4)
  - Letter from Louis T. Wigfall, May 6, 1852; 250061 (Box 5)
  - Stock certificates to Sewanee Mining Co., June 8, 1854; 250060 (Box 5)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Hamman vs. Bader, 1857 - 1858; 250059 (Box 5)
  - Case Listings (with filing dates), 1857 - 1878; 250058 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous legal documents, 1858 - 1884; 250057 (Box 5)
  - Tax receipts of Thos Aycock, 1859 - 1867; 250056 (Box 5)
  - Account sheets of W.H. Hamman, 1859 - 1875; 250055 (Box 5)
  - Legal papers and correspondence (with field notes) - Mauchaka land, 1859 - 1888; 250054 (Box 5)
  - Legal correspondence re. land titles - Francis White, 1860 - 1867; 250053 (Box 5)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Smith vs. Young, 1860 - 1877; 250052 (Box 5)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. ownership of Thomas de la Vega lands, 1860 - 1884; 250051 (Box 5)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land - B.F. Hammond, 1860 - 1889; 250050; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land leases, oil and gas fields, 1860 - 1890; 250049 (Box 6)
  - Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus and Opinion granting same for three men elected Justice of the Peace, 1864; 250048 (Box 6)
  - Deeds of Trust and Powers of Attorney from heirs of Allen C. Reynolds Survey, Robertson County, 1865 - 1868; 250047 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence re. Veatch land, 1866; 250046 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers of Hamman and Mason, and Hamman and Kirkpatrick re. Meerschaum (mineral) with articles of agreement, 1866 - 1867; 250045 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. Daniel's land case, 1866 - 1883; 250044 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Jos. G. McMinn, 1866 - 1889; 250043 (Box 6)
  - Checks, receipts, deposit slips, etc., 1866 - 1890; 250042 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land, etc. - J.C. Roberts, 1866 - 1892; 250041 (Box 6)
  - Civil dockets, District Court, Robertson County, 1867 - 1868; 250040 (Box 6)
  - Judgement and certificate of settlement in W.H. Hamman and J. T. Garnett vs. B. F. Hammond and William Chappell, 1867 - 1876; 250039 (Box 6)
  - Papers of the estate of J.C.C. Brettell (administered by W.H. Hamman), 1867 - 1879; 250038 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. minerals, etc., 1867 - 1889; 250037 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Robert M. Elgin and A.S. Norwood, 1867 - 1890; 250036 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence of Aycock and Hamman, Law firm, 1868 - 1881; 250035 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. Nixon land, 1868 - 1893; 250034 (Box 6)
  - Deeds re. property purchased by Hamman in Calvert, Tx., 1869 - 1875; 250033 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Edward McMillan, 1869 - 1877; 250032 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. consolidation of Texas Timber and Prairie Railroad Co. With Texas Midland, Gulf and New Orleans Railway Co., 1870 - 1874; 250031 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. Viesca lands (includes translation of title to Jose Maria Viesca), 1870 - 1890; 250030 (Box 7)
  - Legal and Business papers and correspondence between Francis M. Adams and W. H. Hamman, 1871 - 1886; 250029 (Box 7)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. purchase of Hensley Tract in Robertson County by J.C.P. Hammond, 1872 - 1873; 250028 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - Willmarth Fisher, 1872 - 1875; 250027 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1872 - 1890; 250026 (Box 7)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Youngu (er?), 1873 - 1881; 250025 (Box 7)
  - Notes and correspondence re. land - Marquez Grant (Maria de la conception Marquez), 1873 - 1884; 250024 (Box 7)
  - Legal papers - William Bowman, 1873 - 1885; 250023 (Box 7)
  - Legal papersn - Littlefield vs. Ogilvie, 1874; 250022 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - P.L. Hammond, 1874 - 1877; 250021 (Box 7)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - E.T. Robinson, 1874 - 1880; 250020 (Box 7)
  - Legal papers re. land involved in Reuben O'Neal vs. A.V. Callen, 1874 - 1880; 250019 (Box 7)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Andrew Cunningham, 1874 - 1883; 250018 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - Jane A Barksdale, 1874 - 1890; 250017 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - H.M. Glass, 1875 - 1877; 250016 (Box 7)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. William Kerr lands in Fort Bend County, 1875 - 1885; 250015 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - J.M. Hook, 1876; 250014 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - J.G. Reeves, 1876 - 1877; 250013 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - R. Tompkins, 1876 - 1877; 250012 (Box 7)
  - Legal documents - Sample vs. Williams, ca. 1877; 250011 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - N. Deans, 1877; 250010 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence from John Steward and J.H. Markoe (?), 1877 - 1881; 250009 (Box 8)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. Barton and Hoard Case in Robertson County, 1877 - 1885; 250008 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - James Lowndes, 1878; 250007 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - S. Bottom, 1878; 250006 (Box 8)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. Knapp land case, 1878 - 1890; 250005 (Box 8)
  - Printed rules of the courts and case statements, 1879 - 1882; 250004 (Box 8)
  - Costs of suit - Tuidall vs. Pierce, 1879 - 1883; 250003 (Box 8)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. Post Hole Augers patents, 1880 - 1884; 250002 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - J. Mussina (with photograph and death card), 1880 - 1889; 250001 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - R.A. Davis, 1881 - 1882; 250000 (Box 8)
  - Legal documents and reports re. the Huntsville, New Orleans and Western Texas Railway Co., 1881 - 1882; 249999 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence re. case of George T. Robertson, 1881 - 1883; 249998 (Box 8)
  - Cost statement in Lawdermilk vs. Lawdermilk, March 2, 1882; 249997 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - J.F. Magale (D. Leavitt), 1882; 249996 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - A.J. Sewell, 1882; 249995 (Box 8)
  - Letters from Clemmie Mann re. buried money in Orange, 1882; 249994 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - George T. Bartlett, 1882 - 1883; 249993 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - H.T. Plastre (?), 1882 - 1884; 249992 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence re. location of various lands (primarily Leroy Boggus lands), 1882 - 1885; 249991 (Box 8)
  - Legal papers - A. Faulknre vs. W. H. Hamman, 1883; 249990 (Box 8)
  - Legal papers - W.W. Belcher, 1883 - 1884; 249989 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence re. Texas and Louisiana Railway Co. (with articles of association for its incorporation), 1883 - 1884; 249988 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - Acker and Abney law firm, 1883 - 1892; 249987 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - F.H. Prendergast, 1884; 249986 (Box 8)
  - legal papers and correspondence re. Josiah Gilleland, 1885; 249985 (Box 8)
  - Letter and advertisements from U.S. Rocking Grate - Bar Co., 1885 - 1886; 249984 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - Walker, 1885 - 1886; 249983 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence re. James Webb's land (Goliad Co.), 1885 - 1889; 249982 (Box 8)
  - Advertisements for new kinds of heating devices, 1885 - 1890; 249981 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with K.R. Blackshear re. land, 1886 - 1889; 249980 (Box 9)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. industrial plant possibilities (New Birmingham), 1886 - 1889; 249979 (Box 9)
  - Letter from Houston Machine Matters Factory re. Moss Mattresses, Sept. 24, 1887; 249978 (Box 9)
  - Printed copy of opinion by Attorney General James S. Hogg, Oct. 8, 1887; 249977 (Box 9)
  - Cherokee City memoranda, ca. 1887; 249976 (Box 9)
  - Certificate of analysis for iron, ca. 1887; 249975 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - J. Carl Smith, 1887; 249974 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence re. S.H. Martin and land division, 1887 - 1888; 249973 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence re. minerals and lithographic stone in Llano and Burnet Counties, 1887 - 1890; 249972 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - T.L. Larkin, 1887 - 1890; 249971 (Box 9)
  - Prospecta of and correspondence re. Cherokee Land and Iron Co. (New Birmingham), 1887 - 1893; 249970 (Box 9)
  - Letter from A.K. Tengers, Jan. 25, 1888; 249969 (Box 9)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. land in Burnet County, 1888 - 1889; 249968 (Box 9)
  - Papers and correspondence re. stocks and solvency (New Birmingham), 1888 - 1889; 249967 (Box 9)
  - Deeds to A.M. Rushin and J.H. Rowlan (with related letter), 1888 - 1889; 249966 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence and notes re. drilling, refining and use of natural gas, 1888 - 1890; 249965 (Box 9)
  - Prospectus for Llano Improvement and Furnace Co., ca. 1889; 249964 (Box 9)
  - Prospectus for and correspondence re. New Birmingham Iron and Land Co., ca. 1889; 249963 (Box 9)
  - Letter of introduction from Alex Gregg to Rev. T. Hodgeson, Feb. 29, 1889; 249962 (Box 9)
  - Letter from the History Co. to W. H. Hamman re. delinquent account, May 6, 1889; 249961 (Box 9)
  - Joint proposition to towns of Rusk and New Birmingham from from Red River Sabine and Western Railway Co., May 18, 1889; 249960 (Box 9)
  - Letter and advertisement re. The Forum Magazine, Sept. 1, 1889; 249959 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - William E. Rider, 1889; 249958 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence re. Sabine Pass Deep Water Convention, 1889; 249957 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - W.O. Campbell, 1889; 249956 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - Simmons and Crawford law firm, 1889 - 1890; 249955 (Box 9)
  - The Microcosm, a magazine put out by Dr. A. Wilford Hall, 1889 - 1890; 249954 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence and Bill of Costs in W. H. Hamman vs. Kosse Ryo and M.J. Parks, 1889 - 1890; 249953 (Box 9)
  - Letter from Wheeler and Rhodes re. David Aaron vs. R. Oskar, May 10, 1890; 249952 (Box 10)
  - Letter from Hartwell W. Moss, July 10, 1890; 249951 (Box 10)
  - Advertisements. newsclippings re. Harriman, Tenn., 1890; 249950 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence re. minerals (New Birmingham), 1890; 249949 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence - J.C. Conner, 1890; 249948 (Box 10)
  - Reports, by-laws, prospectus, correspondence of the East Tennessee Land Co., 1890; 249947 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence - F.F. Gibson, 1890; 249946 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence re. Cass County Iron Deposits, 1890; 249945 (Box 10)
  - Insurance Table of Longevity, n.d.; 249944 (Box 10)
  - Memorandum re. changes of growth between 1865 and 1875, 249943 (Box 10)
  - Draft of bill re. slownes of courts with letter to Galveston news, n.d.; 249942 (Box 10)
  - Closing statement? - unidentified, n.d.; 249941 (Box 10)